Hello English learners, welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
And I'm Erica.
And today we have a very
special guest in our studio, Dany.
Hi everyone, Dany.
Dany is part of our
EnglishPod team, and
today she's going to help us
with this Chinese New Year's lesson.
It's an intermediate
lesson, but it has a lot
of cultural aspects
about Chinese New Year.
So that's what Dany's going
to help us out with today.
Yes, today we're going to learn a little
bit about Chinese New Year in English.
And we're also going
to learn some language
for describing things
that we're excited about.
Okay, yeah, I'm excited to hear the show.
Okay, so let's listen to
the dialogue now, and
then when we come back,
we'll explain everything.
I'm so excited about Chinese New Year.
When do I get to visit grandma?
Grandma makes the best
dumplings in the world.
Ah, right, sounds to
me like you are more
excited about dumplings
than seeing your grandma.
Of course I'm his grandma too.
I bet she's going to teach
me how to play marjon.
Hey, Dad, are you going to
buy me firecrackers this year?
We're going to have the best fireworks.
I'm really looking forward to letting them.
Son, firecrackers aren't toys.
They're dangerous.
Yeah, fireworks are awesome.
Wow.
Don't you remember?
Last year, when I set up the firecrackers,
you covered both your ears and hit them.
Right behind your mother.
And I was scared because I saw a bug.
That's all.
Really?
Oh, and I can't wait to
watch the dragon dance.
Dad, can I sit on your shoulders this time?
Hey, I offered last year.
Well, anyways, I was just
thinking of the red end loops.
I want to make a list of all the things I'm
going to buy with my red end loop money.
I can't wait.
I'm going to have so much money.
Mom, can I get a pen and a piece of paper?
I want a new transformer
now, two transformers.
I'm going to spray you,
Jack, I'll get a PSP game.
Okay, so Chinese New Year.
A lot of exciting vocabulary here.
Before we get into
describing it, let's look at
the vocabulary that we
saw in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
The first word on language
takeaway, dumplings.
Dumplings.
Well, in Chinese,
we call it straight out,
and it's a very traditional Chinese
food and it's getting very famous now.
Yes, so it's basically
small pieces of dough
with maybe some meat
or some vegetables inside.
And then they are
boiled, usually in a soup, in
a soup, but you can
also have fried dumplings.
Yeah, that's right.
That's really good.
If you know Italian food,
they're really similar to a tortellini.
Exactly.
Or in Latin America,
it's very similar to maybe
an empanada, like a
small little empanada.
Okay.
Marco, what's our next word?
All right, our next word,
firecrackers, firecrackers, firecrackers.
Firecrackers.
This is a firecracker.
Firecrackers are so
common in China, we use it
all the time in all occasions, and especially
on the New Year's Eve, traditionally,
people use it to scare
off the evil spirits.
Evil spirits.
The evil spirit.
Yeah.
Okay.
So on Chinese New Year,
there are millions of firecrackers.
Millions of firecrackers.
Yeah.
Now, there are also a lot of fireworks.
Fireworks.
So fireworks are similar to
firecrackers, but they have lots of lights.
Light.
Yeah.
They go up in the air and explode,
and you see lots of nice colors.
Beautiful colors.
Yeah.
Very popular in Fourth
of July in the United States.
Or New Year's Eve.
New Year's Eve.
Mm-hmm.
Fireworks.
Okay.
Now let's look at our last word, set off.
Set off.
So this is the verb you
would use with firecrackers.
Yeah, it means like
explode the firecracker.
Right.
Set off the firecracker.
Set off the bomb.
Set off fireworks.
Well, let's listen to our
dialogue a second time.
And this time, it'll
be a little bit slower
so that you can understand
the language a bit better.
I'm so excited about Chinese New Year.
When do I get to visit grandma?
Grandma makes the best
dumplings in the world.
Ha-ha.
Right.
Sounds to me like you are more excited
about dumplings than seeing your grandma.
Of course I miss grandma too.
I bet she's going to teach
me how to play Majong.
Hey, Dad, are you going to
buy me firecrackers this year?
We're going to have the best fireworks.
I'm really looking
forward to lighting them.
Son.
Firecrackers aren't
toys, they're dangerous.
No, fireworks are awesome.
Whoa.
Don't you remember?
Last year when I set
off the firecrackers, you
covered both your ears
and hid behind your mother.
Dad, I was scared because I saw a bug.
That's all.
Ha-ha.
Really?
Oh, and I can't wait to
watch the dragon dance.
Dad, can I sit on your shoulders this time?
Hey, I offered last year.
Well, anyways, I was just
thinking of the red envelopes.
I want to make a list of all the things I'm
going to buy with my red envelope money.
I can't wait.
I'm going to have so much money.
Mom, can I get a pen and a piece of paper?
I want a new transformer.
No, two transformers.
The Optimus Prime and
made me the wheel jack.
I'll get a PSP game, ha-ha, and I'll buy
the entire class, lunch at McDonald's.
Okay, so we saw some really great
phrases of describing excitement, right?
So let's start with fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
We have four phrases for you today.
And the first one is I'm so excited about.
I'm so excited about.
So when you say I'm so
excited, it means that you
are really happy that
something is going to happen.
I'm so happy you can't relax.
All right, so you could say I'm so
excited about our vacation next month.
I'm so excited about
opening all my presents.
Exactly.
So excited.
Now, we also saw another really great word.
Very similar to I'm so excited.
Yeah.
I'm really looking forward to.
So this is a little bit
less than excited, right?
A bit less strong.
Right.
Yeah.
So you would say, oh, I'm really looking
forward to meeting your new girlfriend.
Or you can say, I'm really looking
forward to seeing that movie.
Exactly.
So it means you're a little
bit excited, but not so excited.
Yeah, you're happy about something
that's going to happen in the future.
Now let's look at our next phrase
and it's very similar to excited.
I can't wait.
So this is very, very
similar to I'm so excited.
Yes, when you're so excited for
something, you can't wait for it.
Let's listen to some more
examples of I can't wait.
Example one.
I'm so excited.
I can't wait to see you.
Example two.
Mmm, smells delicious.
I can't wait for Lena.
Sample three.
I can't wait to open my presents.
So we can use it again the same way.
I can't wait to go on vacation next month.
I can't wait to open all my presents.
Exactly.
Now our last phrase, I bet.
I bet.
BET.
So when you say, I bet, it means that
you're pretty sure about something.
You predict it will happen.
Right.
So let's listen to some
more examples of I bet.
Example one.
I bet I'm going to get so much
money for Chinese New Year.
Example two.
Robert Slade, where do you see he is?
I have any stuck in traffic.
Example three.
I bet the boss is going to
give us a big bonus this year.
Well, I guess we're ready to listen
to our dialogue for the third time.
And then when we come back, Danny's going
to tell us all about Chinese New Year.
I'm so excited about Chinese New Year.
When do I get to visit grandma?
Grandma makes the best
dumplings in the world.
Ha ha.
Right.
Sounds to me like you.
I'm more excited about
dumplings than seeing a grandma.
Of course I miss grandma too.
I bet she's going to teach
me how to play marjon.
Hey, dad, are you going to
buy me fire crackers this year?
We're going to have the best fireworks.
I'm really looking
forward to lighting them.
Son, fire crackers aren't toys.
They're dangerous.
Yeah, fireworks are awesome.
Wow.
Don't you remember?
Last year, when I sent
out the fire crackers, you
covered both your ears
and hit behind your mother.
And I was scared because I saw a bug.
That's all.
Really?
Oh, and I can't wait to
watch the dragon dance.
Dad, can I sit on your shoulders this time?
Hey, I offered last year.
Well, anyways, I was just
thinking of the red end loops.
I want to make a list of all the things I'm
going to buy with my red end loop money.
I can't wait.
I'm going to have so much money.
Mom, can I get a pen and a piece of paper?
I want a new transformer now.
Two transformers up in the spine.
You'll check.
Look at the PSP game.
Come on.
Oh, I need to.
So, Dany, what are these
red packets of money about?
So in Chinese, we call it home bow,
and it's basically a bag full of money.
Why do you get money?
As a gift.
Yeah.
The children get it, though.
Only children get it.
Wow.
If you're a university student and
you haven't got a job yet, then you
can still ask for home bow
from your parents or relatives.
So is there some meaning
to this gift of money?
Well, it is believed that children
have to put these red end loops under
the pillow on your seat to
scare away the evil spirits.
Again, like the firecrackers.
I can't even speak.
A lot of evil spirits in China.
So, Dany, how much money would
a kid get for Chinese New Year?
Well, when I was
little, the best year I got
was 3,000 RMB, which
is like almost $500.
Wow.
Yeah.
I was so rich.
I'm amazing.
Uh-huh.
What about this game, Majung?
Majung?
Majung.
Have you played it?
No.
Um, at the end, again, it's a very
traditional Chinese game and you will see
senior people always
gathering along the table.
So old people?
Old people?
So it's like a board
game, kind of like chess?
It's kind of like chess, but they have
my special, especially made chess.
Oh.
It's very different.
Okay.
So I want to know more about these fireworks
and firecrackers on Chinese New Year.
Okay.
Usually we buy firecrackers.
Yep.
So fireworks are more expensive,
so we play firecrackers, power junk.
And usually we do it right after the
midnight, so 12 o'clock, that's very loud.
And say, for example,
I personally don't
even dare to stay close
when they set off the
firecrackers because
it's just way too loud.
Yeah.
And everyone starts to lie to
them, so it's like, no, it's amazing.
That's pretty.
And I've, I've seen Chinese
New Year three times
in China and each time
I've just been amazed.
Like, it's so, so cool and
so noisy and so awesome.
I mean, you've got to
visit China to see this.
Yeah, yeah.
It's a really cool festival.
Yep.
And definitely playing
with firecrackers is
always fun, so maybe
a little bit dangerous.
Yeah.
Well, everyone, we've
just learned about how
new years is celebrated
in China and we want
to know how do you celebrate
New Year's in your country?
Exactly.
How do you welcome the new year?
How do you scare away evil spirits?
Right?
Yeah.
So come to our website at
englishpaw.com and leave us your comments.
That's right.
Danny, Erica, and I
will be there to answer
all your questions, so be sure
to send us some comments.
Well, everyone, thanks for listening.
And until next time, bye.
Bye.